<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods government of his church, and the deputation thereof to men both for the civill and ecclesiastical estate : especially for the ecclesiasticall, concerning which many doubts and debates are now moved.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42933</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G958</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12181152</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12181152</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55646</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42933)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55646)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 762:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods government of his church, and the deputation thereof to men both for the civill and ecclesiastical estate : especially for the ecclesiasticall, concerning which many doubts and debates are now moved.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 49 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Providence and government of God.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55646:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55646:1"/>
            <p>GODS GOVERNMENT OF HIS CHURCH, AND THE DEPUTATION THEREOF TO MEN, Both for the CIVILL and ECCLESIASTICAL Eſtate: Eſpecially for the Eccleſiaſticall, concerning which many doubts and debates are now moved.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 8. VER. 15, 16.</bibl>
               <p>By mee Kings raign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Princes decree Juſtice.</p>
               <p>By mee Princes, and Nobles, even all the Judges of the earth rule.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:55646:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55646:2"/>
            <head>GODS GOVERNMENT OF HIS CHURCH.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ome Heathen, becauſe they were regardleſſe of the maine paſſages of the world, and others, becauſe they did too curiouſly meaſure them by the line of humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, erred in their opinion, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that God tooke not care of this inferiour world: But ſuch among them, as were more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and better ſighted, made no queſtion but that God had not onely an all-ſeeing eye of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to behold and regard, but alſo an eye intent to the ballancing of mens actions; and, in effect, ſaid, that God was well pleaſed, and would in mercy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55646:3"/>ſooner or later reward them who continued in well doing, and would puniſh thoſe in this life or another, who were given up to doe evill.</p>
               <p>Chriſtians have more undoubted knowledge of theſe things then others, and well underſtand, that God hath a ſpeciall eye on mankind, and hath not left men to themſelves, becauſe they are prone to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in judgement, and miſ-carriage in their actions; as having of themſelves more ſaile in their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, then ballaſt in their underſtanding and will: and therefore that God, as of right hee may, ſo of his ſingular goodneſſe he doth take care to governe and inſtruct the ſons of men.</p>
               <p>This the Holy Scripture maketh evident unto us, when God is ſtiled <hi>The Lord, and Father of all,</hi> and all men ſaid to be at his command and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, his dutifull ſons, or rebellious children. So when he is called <hi>the Maſter of the houſhold,</hi> and all the world his family; <hi>The Builder of his Church,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king choice of fit ſtones, for the rearing up of the ſame; <hi>The Shepheard of the flocke,</hi> and all the world his ſheep or goats; <hi>The Lord of the vineyard,</hi> and all people his pleaſant plants, or fruitleſſe trees.</p>
               <p>That we might take more ſpeciall notice hereof, God is ſtiled <hi>The Ancient of dayes, The King of kings, The Prince of the Kings of the earth, The Biſhop of our ſoules, The great Shepheard of the ſheep, The Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi or great teacher of his people, The head of the Church, and of all Principality and power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By theſe Titles of God, and all other the like in Scripture, wee can attaine but in part, and in ſome ſmall meaſure to the knowledge of his Majeſty,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55646:3"/>wiſedome and excellency: For this Well is vaſt and deep, and our pitchers narrow mouth'd, and of ſmall capacity; yet may wee obſerve, that theſe things attributed to God, doe in moſt eminent and ſuperlative manner belong unto him. So that as God is the great Shepheard of the ſheep, and King of kings, ſo he is likewiſe the great both Judge and Biſhop of our ſoules, and Ancient of dayes; and the Judge of judges, and Biſhop of the biſhops of our ſoules, and the Ancient of all ancients of dayes.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the world, God often ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe unto, and in more familiar manner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed and ſpake with the Patriarchs, and thereby moſt clearly manifeſted his love and care of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, his authority and wiſedome to overſee and order, to governe and teach them, and to expreſſe the actions which are correſpondent unto the titles above ſpoken of. This was a wonderfull condiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending of his infinite Majeſtie to humane weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and an extraordinary favour to ſome ſpeciall inſtruments of his glory for the good of others his people, and not the uſuall way, in which hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to walke; as appeareth by the hiſtory of after times.</p>
               <p>But greater love and mercy did God ſhew, when the ſon of God tooke our nature upon him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed among men thirty and odde yeares; when, I ſay, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, borne King of the Jewes, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heire of David</hi> (though refuſed by the Jews, and their Rulers) <hi>became obedient to death, even to the death of the croſſe,</hi> and performed all things requiſite
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55646:4"/>and fore-appointed by God for mans ſalvation and redemption; and having delivered all doctrine and inſtruction by his owne ſermons, and his Apoſtles preaching and writings, in which were compriſed all <hi>neceſſary matters for the working of faith in us, that in beleeving wee may have eternall life through Chriſts name,</hi> he left the world to make uſe of the ſame <hi>by the comfort of the Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſent down unto them, and ſits on the right hand of his Father in heaven, and as Lord and Chriſt rules and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates all things here below, as having all ſoveraigne power, and authority in heaven and earth given unto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Gods Deputation of the Government of the Church to men before Chriſts time, and how it was practiſed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN regard that <hi>man</hi> (as God himſelfe ſaid) <hi>is but duſt,</hi> and of a fraile nature, and (as the chiefe Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Iſrael felt at Gods terrible and dreadfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livery of the Law) humane imbecility is not able to endure Gods glory and majeſtie, nor to heare his immediate voyce: and becauſe if God, making much leſſe appearance of Majeſty, ſhould goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with men in their proceedings, hee ſhould (as he told Moſes) <hi>conſume them in the way, if they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came</hi> (which they are prone unto) <hi>a froward, rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſtiffe-necked people.</hi> In regard, I ſay, that theſe dangers would befall mankind, as alſo for
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55646:4"/>many other reaſons, well did the Iſraelites ſay to Moſes, <hi>Talke thou with us, and wee will heare, but let not God talke with us, leſt we dye.</hi> And for this cauſe God hath graciouſly vouchſafed to make over a Deputation to men, and to commit the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and teaching of the people to men called and gifted extraordinarily by himſelfe, or to men ſo qualified by ordinary meanes, as he himſelfe hath preſcribed, and ſo called by men, as he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
               <p>This God hath done, becauſe theſe his Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties being men <hi>compaſſed with like infirmities, and ſubject to like paſsions as others, would moderately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsionate others,</hi> who either through the ignorance of their mindes ſhould fall into errour, or through depravation of their wils and affections, ſhould treſpaſſe in their actions.</p>
               <p>This Deputation of Governours and Teachers appeareth moſt plainly in ſome parts of Scripture, where occaſion was given to explicate it fully, and to have it ſettled exactly; as in Moſes time. For then Moſes firſt educated in Pharaohs court, and afterward flying thence, and becomming for forty years a ſhepheard in Midian; that from a low de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree he might be capable of exaltation, was called by God to be the ſhepheard, captain, and King of Iſrael, for leading Gods people out of Egypt. Of this Moſes God ſaith, that <hi>he ſhould be to Aaron as</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 4.16. &amp; 7.1.</note> 
                  <hi>God;</hi> and made him Judge of his people: And when <hi>Moſes could not hear</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Exod. 18.13</note> 
                  <hi>and end all the controverſies</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſo numerous a people, God bids him take ſeventy cheif Elders of the Tribes,
<note n="c" place="margin">Num. 11.16 Deut. 1.13, 14, 15.</note> 
                  <hi>known to be men of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55646:5"/>courage, fearing God and hating covetouſneſſe,</hi> and to make them <hi>Roshim,</hi> heads of the people, and <hi>Sarim,</hi> captains over thouſands, hundreds, fifties, tens. This is further put in practiſe <hi>Num.</hi> 2. where each of the twelve Tribes hath <hi>Naſi,</hi> one chiefe captain, and the foure captains of <hi>Judah, Reuben, Ephraim, and Dan,</hi> have not onely the command of their own Tribes, but each of them two other captaines, and their Tribes ſubordinate unto them.</p>
               <p>God then alſo appointed <hi>Aaron high Prieſt,</hi> a type of Chriſt our high Prieſt: This <hi>Aaron</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Exod. 22.28 Act. 23.5.</note> was alſo <hi>Naſi, a Prince</hi> of the people, and chief Ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Prieſts Eaſtward by the Tabernacle. The ſons of <hi>Levi,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Num. 3.21, &amp;c.</note> divided according to their families into the <hi>Gerſonites, Coathites, and Merarites,</hi> had three <hi>Neſiim,</hi> captains over them: and
<note n="f" place="margin">Num. 4.28, 32.</note> over theſe <hi>Ithamar,</hi> and <hi>Eleazar ſon of Aaron.</hi> This <hi>Eleazar</hi> was
<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 3.32.</note> 
                  <hi>Pakid,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and is called <hi>Naſi Neſiim, Praelatus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latorum,</hi> Captain of captaines. Alſo <hi>Roſhei Aboth,</hi> the heads of the fathers, or chiefe fathers of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites; are by the ſeventy Interpreters
<note n="g" place="margin">Joſ. 21.1. 1. Chro. 24.31</note> call'd <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patriots</hi> and <hi>Patriarchs:</hi> The ſame Hebrew words come elſewhere in ſpeech of the Prieſts and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, and may not unfitly be ſo tranſlated.</p>
               <p>Againe, when God took <hi>David</hi> from as meane imployment as <hi>Moſes</hi> before, and deputed him King of the twelve Tribes, and ſettled him on the throne, <hi>David</hi> tooke ſome chiefe Elders of the Tribes to be his Princes and Counſellours, and appointed captains of thouſands, and hundreds, and fifties, and tens; and made ſome of his ſons when they were grown up, <hi>Cohenim,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">2. Sam. 8.18.</note> chiefe Rulers or Princes.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:55646:5"/>
               <p>The High Prieſt held his place, as in <hi>Moſes</hi> his time. The Prieſts were by <hi>David</hi> divided into 24. Courſes; 16. Courſes for the ſons of <hi>Eleazar,</hi> and 8. for the ſons of <hi>Ithamar,</hi> who were fewer in number then the ſons of <hi>Eleazar.</hi> Among theſe
<note n="i" place="margin">1 Chr. 24.5.</note> there were ſome <hi>Sarim, Princes of the Sanctuary, and Princes of the Houſe of God.</hi> In each of the Courſes was one <hi>Sar, chief Governour, another</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1 Chr. 24.8, 9, 10. &amp; 18.</note> 
                  <hi>ſecond to him,</hi> the reſt were under them: For this term <hi>Sar</hi> is uſed, as of the
<note n="l" place="margin">1 Chr. 27.22.</note> 
                  <hi>chiefe Rulers</hi> over the other Tribes, ſo of the <hi>chiefe Rulers</hi> of the Tribe of <hi>Levi;</hi> and thoſe were chiefe in place in theſe Courſes and in the 24. Courſes of the Levites, who, in regard of their many yeers, and fatherly
<note n="m" place="margin">1 Ch. 15.22</note> experience, and <hi>ability to direct and inſtruct</hi> the inferiour ſort, did diſpoſe of them which were of their Courſes, according to their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties and knowledge in the Prieſtly and Leviticall imployments: So that ſome were <hi>Poſhei Aboth,</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs, or chiefe fathers in each Courſe, others of their kindred ſubordinate to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Solomon,</hi> as a prudent <hi>Deputy</hi> under God, and a worthy Succeſſor of a bleſſed Father, continued theſe Courſes ſetled by his Father, and performed all things in order, <hi>according to the</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">2 Chr. 8.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Commandement of</hi> David <hi>the man of God.</hi> T'is alſo the commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of other good Kings, as of <hi>Aſa, Jehoſaphas, Ezekiah, Joſiah, Zorobabel,</hi> that they did that which was right in the eyes of the Lord, as did <hi>David</hi> their father, and as <hi>Moſes</hi> had preſcribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jehoſuah</hi> and <hi>Ezra</hi> Prieſts, and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> a reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious noble man, ſtill had an eye <hi>to</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Ezr. 3.2, 10. &amp; 6.18. &amp; 8.16, 20. Neh. 12.7, 12, 22, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and ordinances of</hi> David, and gave <hi>Roſhei Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henim,</hi>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55646:6"/>the heads of the Prieſts their places.
<note place="margin">Ezra. 7.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> alſo had authority <hi>according to the wiſdome of God given him, to ſet up Judges, being men who knew the Law of God, and could teach others to know it; and had power to puniſh refractory perſons with death, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, confiſcation of goods, impriſonment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In times, which the ſacred Story but briefely toucheth, or where Kings and Rulers were not ſo carefull as Gods deputation required, or when ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny ſomewhat interrupted, or violently ſtopt the obſervance of Gods Law, the practice of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation is not ſo expreſſe or cleare: yet ſome foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps thereof, even in the worſt times, are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernable.</p>
               <p>In the firſt times of the world (the Story whereof being of many hundred yeeres, is very briefely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared) we finde <hi>Adam Gods Deputy.</hi> Hee ruled not onely over the reſt of the creatures here below, but over his ſons and poſterity. For if <hi>Cain</hi> (had hee been an obedient ſon to <hi>Adam,</hi> and a faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of God) was to <hi>rule</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>over</hi> Abel, <hi>and</hi> Abel <hi>was to ſubmit to him,</hi> becauſe <hi>Cain</hi> was the elder; it neceſſarily followeth, that <hi>Adam</hi> their father was in the ſame regard to rule over both of them, and their children; and when hee dyed, to leave this deputation of authority to the Patriarchs, according as they were Elders of their Families.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Noah</hi> by Gods command, and his fatherly autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, took his three ſonnes and their wives into the Ark with him; To him and them was the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the new world committed. So then, hee in like manner was Ruler over them and their children,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55646:6"/>and did performe ſacred offices for them, as a <hi>Prieſt or Sacrificer, and a Preacher of righteouſneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sem, Noah</hi>'s ſecond ſonne, but more eminent for piety then the other two, is called <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and was Gods Deputy, and both King and Prieſt of the High God. <hi>How</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 7 4.</note> 
                  <hi>great he was, we are bid to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Abraham,</hi> who is ſtiled <hi>Naſi,</hi> a Prince of God by the Hittites, and as a Prince &amp; Captain marched forth with his ſouldiers to reſcue <hi>Lot</hi> his kinſman taken captive, did often ſacrifice, and yet did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his ſubordination to <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> an higher Prieſt then himſelfe; for to him hee paid the tythe of the ſpoils got by conqueſt. The Patriarchs <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> ſucceed <hi>Abraham</hi> in the ſame depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Job</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Job 1.1. &amp; 29.7.22.</note> alſo was a Prince, and <hi>the greateſt of the ſons of the Eaſt, he ſate in the gates and ſtreets as Judge, he often ſacrificed, his words were waited for as the raine, as the later raine, his ſpeeches</hi> (as it is ſpoken of the Prophets and Prieſts) <hi>dropped into his hearers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In theſe times the way of inſtruction for doctrine, and for reſolution in caſe of doubt, was to
<note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 32.7.</note> 
                  <hi>enquire of their fathers, who ſhould ſhew them, and of their El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> (that is, their Prieſts) <hi>who ſhould tell them;</hi> for this duty in ſpeciall manner belonged to the Fathers and Elders, as they were Prieſts. And that ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Elder was made Prieſt in theſe times, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, becauſe <hi>Abraham</hi> upon ſome thoughts of <hi>his</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 15.2.</note> 
                  <hi>dying childleſſ,</hi> ſaid, that of all the ſoules which he had got to the Lord, Eleazar <hi>of Damaſcus</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 24.2.</note>, <hi>the eldeſt ſervant in his houſe</hi> (and manifeſtly a religious man) <hi>ſhould bee his heire;</hi> that is, not onely enjoy his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55646:7"/>but ſucceed him in the Prieſthood, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the knowledge of Godamong the reſt of his retinue.</p>
               <p>In the times next after <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Joſuah</hi>'s death, it pleaſed God to let the Iſraelites know by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence the evill conſequences of the want of a chieſe Rulet to bee Deputy under God; for thereupon it followed, that
<note n="f" place="margin">Judg. 2.11.12 &amp; 21.25.</note> 
                  <hi>every one did that which was good in his owne eyes.</hi> This gave occaſion to the people to neglect the Prieſts maintenance, and to the Prieſts
<note n="g" place="margin">Judg. 17.8.</note> 
                  <hi>to become ſervile,</hi> and matters both in civill and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall State
<note n="h" place="margin">Judg. 2.12. &amp; 3.7. &amp; 10.13</note> 
                  <hi>to be very corrupt,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry to prevaile;</hi> whereupon God puniſhed them with for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne enemies, famine, and civill warre.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Samuel</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Sam. 3.19, 20.</note> was deputed Gods Prophet, Prieſt and Judge, he took ſpeciall care of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and the obſervance of his Laws. Upon <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> religious performances, and
<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.3.</note> 
                  <hi>the peoples repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> God himſelfe ſupplyed the place of
<note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.12</note> their <hi>King</hi> or Ruler, and all the time of <hi>Samuel,</hi> before <hi>Sauls</hi> raigne, <hi>plagued</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 7.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>the Iſraelites enemies, and gave Iſrael repoſſeſsion of the Lands which in time of the Judges they had loſt</hi> by negligence of the Rulers, and of the Prieſts, at the corruptions of thoſe times doe evince.</p>
               <p>When God, defending his people as their King, was unthankfully rejected, and <hi>Saul annoynted to rule over them,</hi> who in many of his carriages proved an evill Deputy of God, and treſpaſſed ſo far that God rejected him, <hi>Samuel</hi> and the Prieſts in place after him better obſerved and continued the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiaſticall charge.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:55646:7"/>
               <p>After <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Salomons</hi> time, <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> made Gods Deputy over ten Tribes, ſet up Idolatry, caſt out Gods Prieſts, made lewd Prieſts fitting his own humour; and thus ſet up a wicked pattern, which his ſucceſſors imitated, till God ſent Iſrael captive to Aſſur. Now alſo <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and ſome wicked Kings of Judah badly managed the deputation with which God entruſted them: yet the Prieſts, driven from their Cities in Iſrael, were entertained by <hi>Rehobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> and ſetled their abode in Judah and Benjamin.</p>
               <p>There were alſo in thoſe times houſes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſupplyed with Students in Bethel, Gilgal, and Jericho. The
<note n="m" place="margin">2 Kin. 4.23.</note> 
                  <hi>new moons</hi> and Sabbaths were by ſome obſerved; <hi>firſt fruits paid to</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">2 Kin. 4.41.</note> 
                  <hi>the Prophets</hi> by ſome; ſome
<note n="o" place="margin">2 Kin. 10.23.</note> Prieſts, ſervants of the Lord, remained in Iſrael: yea, in the dayes of <hi>Athaliah</hi>'s moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked uſurpation there were <hi>ſome</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">2 King. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>religious Captains of hundreds, and ſome Prieſts obſervant of their courſes,</hi> as wee ſee by one courſe of the Prieſts going out of their charge, another part coming in on the Sabbath, &amp; all of them at good <hi>Iehojadah</hi>'s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand. By theſe religious aſſiſtants help <hi>Iehojadah</hi> ſlue <hi>Athaliah,</hi> and ſeated <hi>Ioaſh,</hi> true heir to the Crown, on the Throne, as Gods Deputy. In his later dayes, and in the dayes of the bad Kings who ſucceeded him, the deputation was corruptly managed, and all good order excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly depraved; ſo that God ſuffered Babel to overcome Judah, and carry the Jewes away captive, as Aſſur had done Iſrael.</p>
               <p>After <hi>Malachies</hi> time, when the neighbouring nations of Egypt and Syria, and
<note n="q" place="margin">1 Mac. 1.11.</note> 
                  <hi>ſome falſe brethren among the Jewes themſelves</hi> cauſed great miſchiefe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55646:8"/>to the people of God, ſo that no King ſate on <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi>'s throne, to take care of the Civill and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall government, yet <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Mac. 1.23</note> 
                  <hi>Sanctuary of God, the golden Altar, the Candleſticke, the Table for the ſhew bread, and the like,</hi> remained untill <hi>Antiochus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanes</hi> tooke them away. <hi>The bookes of the Law, the cuſtomes, and rites, the Sabbaths and feaſts</hi> were kept, untill this wicked tyrant ſought to aboliſh them. Notwithſtanding all preſſures and miſeries befal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this people, <hi>ſome</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1. Mac. 4.56.</note> 
                  <hi>among them endevoured to live according to Gods Laws, paid their</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1. Mac. 3, 49.</note> 
                  <hi>firſt fruits and tithes,</hi> maintained their
<note n="e" place="margin">1. Mac. 3.55.</note> 
                  <hi>Captains of thouſands, hundreds, fifties, tens.</hi> And here when Egypts and Syria's power began by Romes riſing to decline, the Maccabees inflamed with a zeale to their Law and Nation, and incouraged by the peoples ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, were not content with their owne Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall charge, and to blow the trumpets for ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up their peoples valour, valiantly to defend their liberty; but tooke to themſelves the places <hi>of Princes and Captaines,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Mac. 5.3, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and in their owne perſons wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged war againſt their enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In Chriſts time the Phariſees ſate in <hi>Moſes</hi> chair, and taught ſome things well; but loved prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, and badly managed it. There were then ſome religious perſons, as <hi>Symeon, Anna, Joſeph, Mary, Joſeph of Arimathea, and others;</hi> Theſe fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated not from the Jewiſh Church, then much corrupted: <hi>Zacharie</hi> miniſtred in the courſe of his family, and departing to his owne dwelling place, left the miniſtration to other Prieſts ſucceeding in their courſe: And untill the deſtruction of Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55646:8"/>and the Temple, and the ſlaughter or diſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this people, the Rulers of the Jews (in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate preſumption, that the <hi>Meſsias</hi> was not then come, and that yet he ſhould come, and be ſeene in that Temple, and receive the kingdome of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) ſtrove to hold up the Lawes and Ordinances of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> ſo far as the miſeries and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of thoſe times would permit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Gods Deputation of the Government of the Church in and after Chriſts time, and how for the chiefe paſſages thereof it was managed.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the fulneſſe of time <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came, &amp; in his owne perſon did preach, and inſtruct the Jewiſh Nation, who were then very erroneous both for government and doctrine: He found their Rulers to be unworthy husbandmen of Gods vineyard, and that the people did perſevere in the deviations of their factious leaders and blind Prieſts with ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of obſtinacy, and would not admit him, the Lord of the vineyard, to rule over them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forty and odde yeares before the deſolation of the City and Temple (that the Nation might have time to repent) Chriſt began to builde the Chriſtan Church by his owne gracious ſermons, and dying for the ſins of the world, roſe again, and ſent his Apoſtles unto all Nations with the glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Goſpel: and that the work might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper by their miniſtration, <hi>he ſent down the Holy Ghoſt</hi> a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55646:9"/>comforter to his Church and Apoſtles, to leade them into all truth, and to furniſh labourers with abilities for the building of the univerſall Church; For effecting whereof a <hi>diverſity</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1. Cor. 11.4, &amp;c. Rom. 12.4, &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>of gifts, admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, and faculties</hi> were requiſite. Wherefore theſe were beſtowed on the Apoſtles and others <hi>by one Lord, one Spirit, one God,</hi> who worketh all in all, and diſtributeth to every one ſeverally accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his will; that every one might profit, and the members of Chriſts body by their ſeverall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices (as the different parts of a mans body) be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable each to other, and all be uſefull for the good of the whole.</p>
               <p>Nor did Chriſt himſelf only work micacles, but ſhewed in his Apoſtles and other inſtruments a manifeſt concurrence of his <hi>almighty power;</hi> as hee had done in <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> when he fent them for building up of the Iſraelitiſh Church: The caſe is much alike; for now the Roman power and tyranny afflicted the Chriſtian Church, as of old <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did the Iſraelitiſh. But what ever was the power oppoſing Chriſtianity, Chriſt ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felſe not onely to be the great Prophet before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, whom God at that time raiſed like unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> but alſo to bee a mighty King, <hi>going</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Rev. 6.2.</note> 
                  <hi>forth conquering, and ſtill more and more to conquer:</hi> For as when before <hi>Sauls</hi> time, <hi>Samuel</hi> well ordering the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate, and all matters by God committed to his charge, God was <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>King of Iſrael</hi> and mightily defended them againſt their enemies: So when in the primitive times, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſties and their ſucceſſours well managed mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55646:9"/>ſpirituall in the Church, Chriſt ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee their King, and graciouſly protected them, and made the Goſpel to proſper, in deſpite of all malicious and tyrannous deſignes to root it out.</p>
               <p n="1">1. No policy, no ſtrength can prevaile againſt the Almighty, how great ſoever it ſeeme in the eyes of man. Gods wayes are not as worldly mens; and at that time this was his courſe: As <hi>Moſes</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>ſeventy Elders ſubordinate unto him</hi> for deciding ſmaller matters, and eaſing him in his charge of Judging the people; ſo it pleaſed Chriſt (as man, and to ſet a pattern for his Deputies, to uſe ſubordinate officers) to appoint <hi>ſeventy Diſciples</hi> to goe two by two, as labourers into Gods harveſt, into all parts, whither hee himſelfe would come. Chriſt alſo ſent the <hi>twelve Apoſtles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.28. Epheſ. 4.11.</note> the witneſſes of what hee did and ſpake, to call both Jewes and Gentiles to Gods truth: Such <hi>meſſengers of old were Moſes, Aaron, Elias, Eſay, Jeremie, Ezechiel</hi> and other Prophets, whom God <hi>ſent</hi> early and late to bring the old Iſraelites and Jewes out of Egypt and Babel, and what Proſelites they could from their ſuperſtitious errours and wicked wayes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God now alſo endowed ſome of his ſervants with the ſpirit of Propheſie, who, as it ſeemed good to God, did firſt upon extraordinary occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and for the ſpeciall uſe of the Church, foretell things to come: and ſecondly, expounded Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which God for the comfort and inſtruction of his people had formerly given: Prophets of both theſe kindes God of old raiſed for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Jewiſh Church.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:55646:10"/>
               <p n="3">3. God appointed ſome to be <hi>Evangeliſts,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a compendious ſtory of Chriſts life and death, namely <hi>Matthew, Mark, Luke, John;</hi> others <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts</hi> preaching and divulging the ſame in their ſermons, and opening ſom paſſages thereof in their writings: So in times before, from the beginning of the world, God, as he ſaw it neceſſary or expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for the uſe of his Church in divers manners, and divers parts, cauſed the Goſpel of Chriſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption by his name to be preached to <hi>Adam, Noah</hi> and others, and afterward by <hi>Moſes, David, Eſay, Zachary</hi> and <hi>all the</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 1.70. &amp; 18.35. &amp; 24.25. Act. 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Prophets ſince the world began:</hi> And therefore often in the new Teſtament for the chiefe paſſages of Chriſts words and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <hi>what</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhould befall untill his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming,</hi> and for the chief doctrines delivered by the Apoſtles, the Law and the Prophets are uſually cited.</p>
               <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.28. Epheſ. 4.11.</note> God gave ſome to be <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers,</hi> who were to informe their auditors mindes with knowledge of truth, and to direct their practiſe: Such of old were the Prieſts and Levites, interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the Law, which was read and preached eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Sabbath in their Synagogues. Hence the terme <hi>Rabbi</hi> interpreted a <hi>Teacher</hi> or <hi>Doctor</hi> was never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſts time ſo frequently (but in ſome reſpect abuſively, for the beſt things may be abuſed) uſed among the Jewes: Of Chriſts comming at twelve yeares old, among theſe Jewiſh Teachers the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſpeaketh:
<note place="margin">John 3.</note> Chriſt met with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of this kind, Rulers and Teachers in Iſrael. So they of old, who were chiefe in the ſchools of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55646:10"/>the Prophets, were <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Teachers, and did by their ſchollars (as <hi>Paul</hi> did by <hi>Timothy) teach them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>that they might teach others, who in time ſhould bee able to teach.</hi> And whereas God frequently calleth the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael his ſheepe, they who fed them with ſound doctrine, and led them on in the practice of Godlineſſe, were of old their Paſtors or Shepheards, and from them is the term borrowed in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Chriſt enabled ſome <hi>to work miracles</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm tion of the doctrine of the Goſpel in the firſt publiſhing thereof, and for the more ſpeedy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of the Gentiles from under the Romiſh tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſuperſtition; as he had done of old, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of Iſrael from out of Egypts bondage and Idolatry, and as hee did at other times upon divers juſt occaſions.</p>
               <p n="6">6 God gave to ſome <hi>the gift of healing</hi> the bodies of men infirme or diſeaſed, that the world might bee more ſenſible, and ſeriouſly conſiderate of cures done upon their ill affected ſoules: Such cures were of old wrought in taking away of ſome of the plagues of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, the Leproſie of <hi>Miriam</hi> and <hi>Naaman,</hi> the deadly diſeaſe of <hi>Ezekiah,</hi> the raiſing from death the Widow of Sarepta's and the Sunamites children, the dead ſouldier, and other the like.</p>
               <p n="7">7 God appointed ſome to bee <hi>helpers,</hi> ſuch as by their company conſent in the truth, and any ſervice of love were taken unto the Apoſtles and Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men, when they journyed from nation to nation: In this kind went together <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnahas, Act.</hi> 11.25, 30. <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>John</hi> called <hi>Mark, Paul</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55646:11"/>
                  <hi>Silas, Acts</hi> 15.93, 41. <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Eraſtus, Acts</hi> 19.22. and <hi>Paul, Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Titus, Gal.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Tychicus, Epheſ.</hi> 6.21. They alſo were helpers whoſe names are joyned with <hi>Paul</hi>'s in ſome of his Epiſtles, as <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. and <hi>Soſthenes,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.1. Of this number alſo may they be counted, who miniſtred unto the labourers in Gods harveſt of their ſubſtance, and ſupplied them with neceſſaries.</p>
               <p n="8">8 God alſo gave <hi>Governments,</hi> ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by a borrowed word, moſt properly ſpoken of governours of Ships. By this terme the Spirit ſeemeth to allude to the entertainment which the Church of God ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in the world, that is toſſed, as a ſhip in the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blous and dangerous ſea: and partly to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a ſhip, where care is ever taken to have a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and maſters mate, and
<note n="*" place="margin">So the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were ſent two by two: and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles travelling took a helper with each of them.</note> double officers in ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall places, that if the firſt in place miſ-carry, the mate may be ready to ſucceed; or if both ſubſiſt, the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour on any occaſion of ſickneſſe, wounds, weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or otherwiſe, may ſupply the place of the ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour. The like care was of old taken among the Prieſts, for <hi>Aaron</hi> had <hi>Eleazar,</hi> and upon <hi>Aarons</hi> death <hi>Eleazar</hi> had <hi>Phinees;</hi> their ſeconds. In each of the foure and twenty Orders or Courſes of Prieſts and Levites there was one chiefe, and each of the chiefe had a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Chro. 24.8, 9, 10, &amp; 18.</note> adjoyned to him; ſuch it ſeemeth was our Anceſtors care, who to a Biſhop ſubordinated a Dean, and to a Rector of a Pariſh, a Vicar.</p>
               <p n="9">9 To ſome Chriſt gave ability <hi>to ſpeake divers tongues:</hi> By this gift of God many were converted at Pentecoſt after Chriſts aſcenſion, many after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: This gift was fore-propheſied of, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55646:11"/>
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. from <hi>Joel</hi> 2. and 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. from <hi>Eſay</hi> 28.11. Some uſe there was of divers tongues before Chriſts time; for then many Proſelytes were won out of Nations differing in ſpeech from the Jewes; yet not by any miraculous gift of tongues but by the Hebrew or ſome other tongue attained in an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way.</p>
               <p>No one perſon had all theſe gifts, for <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Are all Apoſtles? are all Prophets? are all Teachers?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.29.</note> 
                  <hi>are all Workers of Miracles,</hi> and ſo forth: Each one had ſuch indowments as God pleaſed to give, and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion incident ſeemed to require.</p>
               <p>Some one had many of theſe gifts, though no one man all. Saint <hi>John</hi> was an Apoſtle, an Evangeliſt, a Prophet, a Teacher; Saint <hi>Paul</hi> was an Apoſtle, a Prophet, a Teacher, had ability to ſpeake many tongues: theſe two might have ſom other of the gifts above-named; ſo might other of the Apoſtles, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, Presbyters, in like manner, have divers of the adminiſtrations and operations.</p>
               <p>Other titles, which are elſewhere in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament given to ſuch inſtruments as Chriſt pleaſed to imploy for the propagation of the Goſpel, doe fall within the compaſs of theſe, and are co-incident with ſome of them here above ſpecified: For <hi>Biſhops, Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, Deacons, Angels of the Churches, Embaſſadours, Builders of the Church, husband men in Gods field,</hi> are of like nature with theſe.</p>
               <p>Of theſe titles no one is wholly new, but every one of them upon ſome occaſion leſſe or more ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the times under the Law, and made uſe of heretofore. Hence it may be that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55646:12"/>that hee did in the miniſtration of the Goſpel <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, do the part of a ſacrificing Prieſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.16. that is, in ſome part of their ſacred office, not in ſacrificing, but in preaching, praying, and the like. Only, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> was greater then any Prophet before, (for he did ſay, <hi>This</hi> Jeſus <hi>whom here you ſee is the Lamb of God,</hi> who ſhall dye for you: He taketh away the ſins of the world, ſo that in him all Nations of the earth ſhall bee bleſſed) ſo theſe other meſſengers ſent forth &amp; gifted by Chriſt, were greater then he in this, that they could ſay, Chriſt hath dyed, and roſe againe, and taken away the ſins of the world, and extends his mercy both to Jewes and Gentiles.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the King of kings, and the Prieſt after the order of <hi>Melchiſedech,</hi> and according to the times before the Law given to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and coming of the Tribe of Judah (to which the Prieſthood did not belong by the ordinances of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law) did provide (notwithſtanding the Romans tyranny) <hi>Deputies</hi> to inſtruct, and to take order for the inſtruction of the people: Theſe Deputies he choſe not out of <hi>Aarons</hi> Tribe, but Jews, without reſpect unto any other Tribe in ſpeciall; and called them not <hi>Hieries,</hi> Sacrificers, as of old; but by other titles not unknowne to the Jewes: and ſuch was the nature of theſe titles, that they expreſſed their miſſion, overſight, teaching, adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and their manifold care to be diligently imployed for the good of the Church. Of theſe ſome were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhermen, and unlettered, as <hi>Andrew</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that the Goſpels propagation might be knowne to be of God, and not to depend on, or ſubſiſt by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdome: others had parts more eminent for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55646:12"/>learning, as <hi>Paul,</hi> brought up at <hi>Gamaliels</hi> feete, and <hi>Apollos</hi> commended for his eloquence, and other the like: that when extraordinary gifts ſhould ceaſe, the helpe of Arts, and humane learning and education, if chriſtianly and religiouſly managed, might be knowne to be of good uſe. However, were Chriſts inſtruments literate, or unlearned, he furniſhed them with gifts for diſcharge of their callings. He preſcribed, that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>whom the holy Spirit led into all truth,</hi> and who under Chriſt had each of them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Biſhoprick,</hi> and that Apoſtolick men approved and appointed by them, ſhould, as a <hi>Titus left by S.</hi> Paul <hi>in Crete,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> ordaine Officers in Gods Church, who ſhould be in many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects religiouſly qualified, <hi>able to teach, convince, &amp;c.</hi> and to ordaine things which were wanting. So in the beginning of the world, men gratiouſly qualified, and walking with God, as <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> were Gods Prophets and Teachers, and <hi>Cains</hi> wicked ſons of the elder houſe paſſed by: ſo <hi>Japhets</hi> the elder brothers ſons were diſperſed at Babels building, and <hi>Sems, the younger brothers</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 9.27.</note> 
                  <hi>tents</hi> conſpicuous for religion: So <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob</hi> were pious men and Gods Prieſts, and <hi>Nahor Iſmael,</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> the elder brethren paſſed by. So now <hi>Christ,</hi> as he hath no ſpeciall Tribe of Iſrael, ſo neither to any prerogative of birth, but in the ordinary courſe requireth that men be choſen into ſacred offices, who be well gifted for the diſcharge of the ſame. And to this end the Apoſtles took to them one or more of the <hi>Chriſtian Diſciples</hi> to accompany them, and to miniſter unto them, that theſe ſeeing the Apoſtles practice, and hearing their doctrine, might in due time be ſerviceable to Gods Church, as of old the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55646:13"/>Prophets of God had done, by educating ſome ſons or ſchollers under them; and as out of the perſons which accompanied the Apoſtles in <hi>Chriſts</hi> life time <hi>Matthias</hi> (but here <hi>Chriſts</hi> authority by a religious lot was uſed, becauſe hee immediately called the other Apoſtles) was choſen.</p>
               <p>As the <hi>ſacred offices</hi> were correſpondent, and in great part the ſame with thoſe in <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; ſo the <hi>doctrine taught in the new Teſtament</hi> is the ſame in ſubſtance, and not much differing from that which formerly was openly, or in types or cloſer ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifications delivered by <hi>Moſes</hi> &amp; the Prophets. <hi>Things done to Chriſt were foretold by</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prophets, Luk.</hi> 18.31. &amp; 24.25. <hi>Chriſt reſtoreth all things ſpoken of by the Law and the Prophets, Act.</hi> 3.21. <hi>All the Prophets witneſſed, that by his Name ſalvation ſhould come to the Gentiles, Act.</hi> 10.43. The ſum of the Law was, <hi>The loue of God above all, and the love of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour as our ſelves, ſalvation by faith in Chriſt,</hi> and that which is the effect thereof, <hi>holineſs of life,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9, 10 and 16. The new Teſtament treateth upon the ſame Theames.</p>
               <p>Beſides, As <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old <hi>was Gods people, a Kingdom of Prieſts, an holy Nation, Exod.</hi> 19.6. ſo under the Goſpel <hi>God hath choſen a generation, a royall Prieſthood, an holy nation, nation, a peculiar people,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9. <hi>God of old
<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> was known in Jewry, &amp; ſalvation was of the Jews.</hi> Now alſo there are the <hi>Jews</hi> indeed, and the
<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Iſrael of God,</hi> thoſe who know God in Chriſt; and <hi>he</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 2.28.</note> 
                  <hi>is not a Jew who is one outward in the fleſh, but he is one who is one within in the heart, whoſe praiſe is not onely of men,</hi> that his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren ſhould praiſe him, <hi>but of God alſo,</hi> by whom to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55646:13"/>be praiſed argueth a true praiſe indeed. And now the old Jeruſalem being demoliſhed, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 4.26.</note> 
                  <hi>from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove is the true mother of us all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is alſo a great correſpondence between the enemies of Gods people then, and of true Chriſtian now. Then was <hi>an enmity between the ſeed of the woman and the ſeed of the ſerpent:</hi> Chriſt in his time found <hi>a generation</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 23.33.</note> 
                  <hi>of vipers or ſerpents</hi> oppoſing him. <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Apoc. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>and his Angels,</hi> Apoſtles, and others were fought <hi>againſt by the Dragon and his Angels,</hi> or inſtruments. A late upſtart perſecuting <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babel</hi> exerciſe cruelty on the Chriſtian Church, as the former Egypt and Babel did on Gods people. Sundry croſſes betided <hi>Iſrael formerly in the wilderneſſe;</hi> the Church under the Goſpel is again driven <hi>into the</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Apoc. 12.6.</note> 
                  <hi>wilderneſs,</hi> and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly ſtill maintained by Gods hand as before; ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Gog</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Apoc. 20.8.</note> and <hi>Magog</hi> fight againſt the Church in theſe laſt dayes, as in former times. There were <hi>falſe Prophets</hi> among Gods people of old, and a
<note place="margin">1 Jude 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſſe; ſuch there are now, <hi>who ſpare not the flock, wolves</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Act. 20.29.</note> 
                  <hi>in ſheeps cloathing:</hi> There were before a <hi>Jannes and Jambres</hi> who reſiſted <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſo now <hi>there</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> 
                  <hi>are ſome who reſiſt the truth:</hi> There was of old a <hi>gainſaying of</hi> Koreh <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt</hi> Moſes <hi>and the Prieſts</hi> in ſacred adminiſtration above others, as if God had made a parity; the like gainſaying to that of <hi>Koreh</hi> is foretold to been <hi>in</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Jude 11.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe laſt times.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So then, ſeeing God giveth us no new Scripture over and above the old and new Teſtament, but of his great mercy hath left them unto us for to direct our judgements and practice; to them both we ought care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55646:14"/>to attend: The old Teſtament was made uſefull, and was ſufficient for the Jewiſh Church; the old and new together have whatſoever is neceſſary for theſe laſt times. We muſt fetch our inſtruction from both; and therefore the new often relateth to the old, for the old is of great uſe ſtill in very many things, and the equity ſtill remaines of many obſervances, types, and ceremonies, which themſelves are not to bee uſed. Chriſt fulfilled, and put an end to ſome of them, as <hi>the ſacrifices</hi> and <hi>Paſchal lamb,</hi> which typed Chriſts dying for our ſins, and <hi>Jonas</hi> type ſhewing his riſing againe the third day: the obſervance of <hi>beasts cleane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,</hi> ſhewing a diſtinction of Jews and Gentiles, and ſome other the like. Yet when Chriſt had fulfilled theſe, and put a period to their obſervance, ſome in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction thence is to bee raiſed to our ſelves; as thus, Chriſt was offered up as a ſacrifice for us, and dyed on the Groſſe; wee therefore muſt not
<note n="p" place="margin">
                     <hi>As Paul,</hi> Act. 20.24.</note> 
                  <hi>refuſe to dye for the Goſpel,</hi> and muſt
<note n="q" place="margin">Col. 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſacrifice and mortifie our luſts.</hi> Chriſt was the true <hi>Paſcha,</hi> and ended that type, but in ſtead of it inſtituted the Lords Supper: Chriſt, as <hi>Jonas,</hi> roſe againe the third day, we muſt riſe from the death of ſin: the Gentiles were as beaſts unclean, but Chriſt purifying their hearts by faith, they are become clean, and fellow heires, and one body with us; yet even to this day <hi>wee</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.14.</note> 
                  <hi>muſt not bee unequally yoked by marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with infidels, nor</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Theſ. 3.6.</note> 
                  <hi>communicate with ſuch as walk inordinately.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other rites and ceremonies there be in the Law, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> do directly concern us, yet their literal obſervance is utterly taken away, as namely, the <hi>ſeventh daies Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> anſwerable to Gods reſting from creating the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55646:14"/>world, was fulfilled and ended by Chriſts body reſting that day in the grave; but yet a <hi>new</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 4.10.</note> 
                  <hi>day of reſt</hi> comes in place of it, <hi>the Lords day,</hi> in which Chriſt reſted from the work of our Redemption. <hi>Circumciſion</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhed, yet <hi>circumciſion of heart</hi> and lips are ſtill of uſe: And as a Jewiſh child was to be circumciſed the eighth day, ſo ought a Chriſtians child to be baptized in its infancy, though Chriſt hath not expreſſely injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this in the new Teſtament. The Iſraelites were to keep the <hi>Paſchal feaſt</hi> to expreſs their belief in Chriſts deliverance of them to come, and their thankfulneſſe for the ſame; ſo, hath not the Chriſtian Church well ordained a <hi>ſolemn Eaſter feaſt</hi> in memory and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for our deliverance from a worſe bondage pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by Chriſt? The Jews kept a <hi>feaſt at Pentecoſt,</hi> in memory of Gods giving them the Law at that time; and hath not the Chriſtian Church well appointed us to obſerve with thankfulneſſe <hi>our Pentecoſt?</hi> at which time Chriſt ſent downe the holy Ghoſt on the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and others, inabling them to write for us the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and to deliver unto us all neceſſary, ſaving, and comforting truth: and if the Jewes lawfully kept <hi>the feaſt of dedication,</hi> inſtituted for the memory of Gods mercy unto them after <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes</hi> profana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sanctuary, as verily they did, (for Chriſt witneſſed thereunto
<note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 10.22.</note> 
                  <hi>by his obſervance of that feaſt</hi>) much more may wee lawfully in a thankfull remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of any great deliverance or favour of God, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a <hi>ſolemnity which publick authority</hi> ſhall ordaine. As the Iſraelites in the wilderneſſe gathered <hi>Manna,</hi> as every one could beſt find it, &amp; laid it down in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon, to bee diſtributed to every family according to their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55646:15"/>need, in regard of the number of their perſons; yet in Canaan every one held <hi>a propriety in their poſſeſsions and goods:</hi> So the Apoſtles and primitive Chriſtians, in caſe of neceſſity, had <hi>all things common</hi> which concerned their preſent maintainance; yet afterward left every man to hold <hi>a propriety in his eſtate and goods.</hi> The <hi>Fire</hi> which deſcended from heaven to burn the ſacrifices, was by the care of the Prieſts to be kept e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver burning and never to goe out: ſo now the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> which came downe from heaven upon the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in the ſimilitude of fiery tongues, is ever to be kept in, and <hi>not to be quenched,</hi> 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.19.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prieſts and Levites,</hi> who in time of the Law
<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.13.</note> 
                  <hi>attended at the Altar,</hi> partaked with the Altar: ſo now, <hi>they which labour in the Goſpel</hi> ought to live of the Goſpel. <hi>The ſacrificing Prieſts and Levites,</hi> teachers of the Iſraelites, had, as the Prieſts in the Patriarchs time, the <hi>tithes, Gods portion</hi> for their maintenance: and God now gives this rule, <hi>that the</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.11.</note> 
                  <hi>miniſtry ſowing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things, ſhould reape of the carnall things ſowed by the Laity.</hi> And in what proportion rather ſhould that be, then in that which was of old <hi>Gods portion,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>a tenth part</hi> of the encreaſe of the ground and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle? And if we upon good ground of the equity of the Law give God, and imploy in ſacred duties every ſeventh day of our whole time, as before was done in the Patriarchs time, and under the Law; hath not likewiſe our Church now well ordained that the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical eſtate ſhould have the tithe of the increaſe of the earth and cattell, as was done in the Patriarchs time, and in the times under the Law? The equity of both is alike. Beſides, the generall Rule of mens
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55646:15"/>bounty or duty in this kind, ſhewing their thankfull acknowledgement to God, was to make the extent thereof <hi>according</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Deut. 16.17. Lev. 5.7, 11. &amp; 14.21. Neh. 5.8. Acts 11.29. 1. Cor. 16.2. 2. Cor 8.12.</note> 
                  <hi>to their ability, and according to Gods bleſsing on their labours, as God hath proſpered their eſtate.</hi> And what can bee more ſutable thereunto then to render unto God a tenth, ever in uſe untill Chriſts time, when by Heathen tyranny it was interrupted? For thus it will come to paſſe, that each man ſhall have nine parts for his owne uſe, and Eccleſiaſticall perſons receive a tenth, and ſo partake in a fit propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the Laity in yeares of plenty and ſcarcity, and condole in affliction, or rejoyce in Gods bounty together with the Laity.</p>
               <p>In the firſt times of the world the Kingly and Prieſtly offices were conjoyned in one perſon, and muſt needs make him of more authority, and require and move the people in their own hearts to ſhew the more reverentiall obſervance in civill and ſacred du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: But afterward, when the burden and charge was become very great, too heavy for one perſon to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe, God appointed <hi>Moſem cuſtodem utriuſque tabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae,</hi> to take the ſpeciall charge of civill matters, and <hi>Aaron of the Prieſtly calling.</hi> And afterward untill Chriſts time, the Prieſts tooke care of the ſacred per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, and were uſually aſſiſtant unto the chiefe Rulers and Kings: as <hi>Eleazer</hi> to <hi>Joſua</hi> in dividing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan, <hi>Zadock</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi> in building the Temple, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoiadah</hi> a preſerver and inſtructor of <hi>Joaſh, Jehoſuah</hi> in commiſſion with <hi>Zorobabel</hi> at the returne from Babel. And as the chiefe Fathers and Princes of the ſeverall Tribes aſſiſted the King in civill matters: ſo the Prieſts and Levites were ſubordinate to the high Prieſt in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55646:16"/>Eccleſiaſticall buſineſſes, and he and they ſubject to the King: ſo now when the Kingdomes and occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſtian Princes are much increaſed, they have made uſe of <hi>Nobles,</hi> being men of eminent parts for civill affaires; and of <hi>Eccleſtaſiicall men,</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous for vertue, religion, prudence and learning in Eccleſiaſticall performances. And as the
<note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 17.9.2. Chro. 19.6, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſts and Levites were in joynt commiſsion with Judges</hi> for the judgement and cauſe of the Lord, whoſe the Judgement is: ſo have ſuch Eccleſiaſticall men, as above, been joyned in Judgement with prudent Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in Courts where Chriſtian Lawes, ſubordinate to Gods Law, and guided in many things by humane reaſon and by cuſtome of the Nations well ſettled, have bin the Rule determining controverſies.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, As the Jews had one ſolemn place for Gods worſhip and ſervice, namely <hi>the Temple in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> where every day ſacrifice was made and holy rites performed, and prayers and praiſes offered up to God; and had alſo <hi>many Synagogues</hi> in their Land for prayer and expounding the word: ſo, have not our forefathers under the Goſpel, being partakers of a better Covenant, and enjoying better promiſes then they of old, well ſhewed their thankfulneſſe to God by building large and goodly Churches for prayer and praiſing God thrice every day, and for frequent preaching in the great Cities of this Land, and yet built in the leſſe townes and villages ordinary and ſmaller <hi>Churches and Chappels</hi> for prayer and preaching at due times? Where God affords more meanes, he requires more duty according to mens a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility: ſo in regard that the great Cities have beene
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55646:16"/>more able to build, furniſh, and maintain Gods Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſervice, they may ſeem religiouſly in this but to have done their duty.</p>
               <p>Yet the equity of this will not extend ſo farre as Rome doth ſtretch it, arrogating to her ſelfe a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency over all the world, and deſiring that all Churches on the earth ſhould vaile to her, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, and be regulated by her; as all Canaans Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, and Eccleſiaſticall perſons received their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection from Jeruſalem. For firſt, in the time of the Law there was ſuch a multiplicity of rites and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and performances, that had not God made the King, his Counfell, and the chiefe Eccleſiaſticall perſons in Jeruſalem to regulate all parts of the Land of Canaan, unity and concord in all points could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have bin obſerved: but in the Chriſtian Church, and in the worſhip and ſervice of God therein, Chriſt ordained few and eaſie Sacraments, a plainer and more familiar doctrine of faith and practiſe, ſo that it is very poſſible to keepe peace and unity, and for Churches in Lands farre remote one from another, to be of one accord and mind, if they will reſt in the ſimplicity of the Goſpel: much more for all the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Churches in our Land to agree one with another in all performances and chief doctrines and neceſſary truths, becauſe they have the ſame plain direction from ſacred Scripture, and one King &amp; Parliament to regulate them. Secondly, whereas God foretold that <hi>many</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Rev. 17.13, 14, 15, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Kings ſhould give power and authority to a tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Beaſt,</hi> and ſhould ſubmit themſelves to the <hi>great City, which then raigned,</hi> (and ever ſince deſired to do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineer) <hi>over the Kings of the earth;</hi> and yet ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55646:17"/>when the Lamb of God, Chriſt, had over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come them, <hi>re-aſſume to themſelves their own power,</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by Chriſt, and ſhould <hi>hate that great City,</hi> called by the Spirit of God, <hi>The Whore, and make her deſolate and naked.</hi> This is in great part already come to paſſe, and Kings and Queens have become nurſing fathers and mothers to the Church; and rightly hold and maintaine that they have ſupreme power in their owne Kingdoms next and immediately under Chriſt the head of the Church, and are as independent of any forraine perſon whatſoever, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> in their times: and therefore that they neither ought nor may be ſubordinate to the Roman Church, which is now manifeſtly proved to have left her firſt love, and to be <hi>The Whore,</hi> whom the Kings of the earth ſhould ruinate.</p>
               <p>But to returne to the obſervances of old. In the Law, from which an equity being deduced is ſtill of uſe in the Chriſtian Church, wee obſerve that there were in thoſe times,
<note n="*" place="margin">This word is often anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, for the courſes of the Prieſts and Levites.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, diverſities of gifts of God, of adminiſtrations, and operations. By Gods ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment and gracious diſpenſation the high Prieſt had the chiefe place, other Prieſts were under him; the Levites, inferiour to theſe, had one chiefe in every degree; the reſt under them had their different admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, ſome were Singers, others Porters. Some of theſe were gifted by God for expoſition of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Prophecy, or making ſacred hymnes, and other holy imployment: So in time of the Goſpel, <hi>There were</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.4, 5, 6.</note> 
                  <hi>diverſity of gifts by one and the ſame Spirit, diverſity of adminiſtrations by one and the ſame Lord, diverſitie of operations by one and the ſame God.</hi> Of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55646:17"/>the Diſciples and ſcholars of Chriſt, ſome were called to be Apoſtles, and Teachers, and Workers of mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, &amp;c. ſome to be Evangeliſts, ſome to be Prophets. Theſe trained up <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants, Deacons, fellow workemen, fellow ſouldiers.</hi> Theſe, according as the Apoſtles pleaſed, and ſaw expedient for the Churches uſe, grew up from Schollars or Diſciples to be helpers or Deacons, and then afterward to be fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low workmen, and fellow ſouldiers with the Apoſtles themſelves; for they of inferiour gifts were to endevour to obtain <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 12.31.</note> 
                  <hi>more excellent gifts:</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> commands. In the Law the chiefe places of the Prieſts and Levites over their brethren came to them by ſucceſſion of bloud, ſo that the hoary head found in the way of a faithfull and right performance of the charge entruſted unto him, upon the death of the <hi>Sar</hi> or <hi>Nagîd,</hi> prince or chiefe man in the high prieſthood, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the 24. Courſes, and the other places, was prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and ſucceeded the deceaſed. But in time of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the Apoſtles and Apoſtolicall men by their appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, having the diſpenſation of matters under their Lord Chriſt committed to them, and obſerving in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall perſons the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, gracious gifts beſtowed by the divine power upon them whom they inſtructed, deſtinated them to adminiſtrations and imployments accordingly: which were diverſified, as was requiſite for the building of Gods Church: For as <hi>in the</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">1 Co. 12.12.</note> 
                  <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body there be divers members of more noble or mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner uſe,</hi> and all, even the meaneſt, very uſefull; ſo 'tis in the Church or body of Chriſt. And in regard that the Church is here militant under Chriſt the chief captain, he hath his under and ſubordinate Captains, they infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour captains under them, and laſtly the common ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55646:18"/>namely each private Chriſtian, who all in their places, civill or ſacred, war under Chriſts banner; for God hath not gifted men with an equality of courage and indowments, and therefore intended not a parity ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Civill or Eccleſiaſticall places. There were of old among the ſacred officers <hi>Sarim, Negidim, Neſiim,</hi> Chieftains, Rulers, Princes of the ſanctuary for the well ordering of the Prieſts in their ſeverall adminiſtrations according to their faculties, who were under them: and doth not the equity of the matter require the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination in the Church of God now? yea it appeareth that the Church of God was ſo ordered in the Primitive times; for <hi>Chriſt</hi> aſcending into heaven ſate there as <hi>King of kings</hi> to preſerve his people, notwithſtanding all Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man tyranny; and appeareth there as <hi>high Prieſt</hi> for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. He ſent twelve Apoſtles, Biſhops under him, into ſeverall parts of the world; they diſpoſed of ſuch ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, as Chriſt in his life time, or themſelves did edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, and inſtruct, and planted <hi>Apoſtolicall men, Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Deacons, their fellow workmen, and the reſt</hi> under o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther titles, as they found the occaſions of Gods Church to require, and people fitted and ready to receive them. This was put in practiſe in the ſeven Churches of Aſia, at Philippi, Corinth, and elſewere: For ſee what courſe was obſerved in ſome few Churches, the like we may conceive of the reſt for their generall carriage.</p>
               <p>The Epiſtles in the Apocalipſe are directed to <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Apoc. 2. &amp; 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Angel of each Church</hi> of the ſeven in Aſia, as denoting one principall man in each: for ſo, <hi>The Lord of the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, The Lord of the Houſe, The Lord of that ſervant,</hi> elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where ſpeeches in form like theſe, imply one ſpeciall Lord, and not many Lords one equall to another. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, in thoſe times there were ſome <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, not men
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55646:18"/>which ſeemed to be eminent and were not, but who were ſuch as they ſeemed, <hi>men</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 2.6, 9.</note> 
                  <hi>of chiefe place</hi> above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, dignified both by God and men; <hi>pillars in Gods Church,</hi> not pillars in the ſame rank as all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are, that is, ſtanding ſtedfaſt in Gods truth; but pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in regard of eminency and adminiſtration above o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſuch were <hi>James, Caiphas, John,</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> taken unto them. Again, God who is
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Architection, The chief builder</hi> of the Church, vouchſafeth the title to St. <hi>Paul</hi> that he is called <hi>an Architecton,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.10.</note> 
                  <hi>a chiefe builder:</hi> which intimates that the other Apoſtles were chiefe builders alſo; and if <hi>Paul</hi> may well be ſtiled <hi>an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>builder,</hi> he may alſo rightly be called <hi>an Archbiſhop.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo St. <hi>John</hi> the Apoſtle was an Archbuilder, &amp; an Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop under Chriſt, <hi>The Archbuilder</hi> and the <hi>Archbiſhop:</hi> For if <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo, the ſame cannot be denyed to <hi>John, Quia ſimilium ſimilis eſt ratio:</hi> Chriſt ſupreme in autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity gives order to <hi>John, John</hi> ſends the Epiſtles to the Angels of the Churches, the Angels receive them for their own and the other Teachers (for there were other Teachers beſides the ſeven Angels) and the peoples in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. This alſo is deducible from the equity of the Law, and the order ſettled among the Prieſts of old; for while <hi>Aaron</hi> the Type of Chriſt was alive, <hi>Eleazar</hi> his ſonne was ſtiled <hi>Naſi Neſiim,</hi> Prelate of prelates, or Chieftain of chieftains; and the chief fathers in the 24. courſes are <hi>Roſhei Aboth,</hi> Archpatriots and Patriarchs. And ſeeing the new Teſtament doth often borrow not onely doctrine, but termes of ſpeech from the old, and that very uſually, may we not judge, that we have <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecton</hi> and <hi>Patriarch, Biſhop,</hi> and the like, borrowed from the old Teſtament? and conceive that in the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, Eaſtern and African Churches, as well as in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55646:19"/>Roman &amp; Weſtern Churches theſe titles and a like ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination of governours have taken place; ſeeing <hi>Paul</hi> calleth himſelf <hi>Architecton,</hi> this warranteth the reſt of like nature.</p>
               <p>Only a care muſt be had that they who have theſe titles 1. muſt not <hi>love</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Mat. 23.6.</note> 
                  <hi>the title or preheminence</hi> belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereunto, nor earneſtly affect to be great in dignity: but, being call'd to any high place, becom, as <hi>Moſes, meek men,</hi> and be truly fathers and overſeers, performing uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervice for the whole Church, where they are thus dignified: for Chriſt forbidding men to be called
<note n="b" place="margin">verſe. 8, 9, 10</note> 
                  <hi>Rabbi, Father, Doctor,</hi> yet in Scripture ſtileth men by the ſame
<note n="c" place="margin">
                     <p>Rabbi is Teacher, and uſuall. Joh. 1.38.</p>
                     <p>Paul a father to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, 1. Cor. 4.15.</p>
                     <p>Barnabas and Silas leaders, Act. 15.22.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>terms;</hi> and therefore doth not abſolutely deny them, but their uſe in the Phariſaicall humour, which was <hi>to love them, and to be proud of them,</hi> that their party might overtop the Sadduces: ſo faction here, as in many other kinds, is chief cauſe of the miſchief. 2. They which have theſe titles <hi>muſt acknowledge their Deputation from God,</hi> and theſe terms due properly and indeed to him, &amp; but lent to them; for ſaith Chriſt, <hi>ye have one Rabbi, Father, Doctor, in heaven:</hi> thoſe in earth are but ſubordinate to him; they muſt not require to be heard in their owne names, but in Chriſts; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord</hi> muſt be their plea. 3. They muſt <hi>not do as the Kings of the earth,</hi> the heathen Roman Lords, then moſt in the Jews eye; who 1. neither
<note n="d" place="margin">Pilate ſaid, Knoweſt thou not that I have power, &amp;c.</note> ruled nor taught according to Gods Law, but by humane reaſon and Laws of their own, in many things very corrupt. 2. they minded an earthly Empire
<note n="e" place="margin">They would have no King but Caeſar to rule all.</note> over the whole world, and domineered therein over the Kings of the earth. 3. promoted their
<note n="f" place="margin">Who can war with the beaſt? Apoc. 13, 4.</note> Soveraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty by the ſword and violent means. 4. made all their acquirements ſerve to the getting of
<note n="g" place="margin">Who is like unto the beaſt. ibid.</note> ſame and glory to themſelves. 5. became gracious
<note n="h" place="margin">See Luk. 3.1</note> Lords to their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55646:19"/>and rewarded them with worldly honours and preferments, and minded not at all the doing of their ſoules good, and the obtaining a better life after this; which are the maine ayme of Chriſts Deputies for ruling and teaching.</p>
               <p>So then, theſe obliquities being avoyded, the titles of <hi>a Patriarch, an Archbuilder, an Archbiſhop</hi> are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves lawfull, being moderatly managed for the ſervice and good of Gods people. God deales in like manner with kings; for though he himſelf be <hi>The King of kings, and the Lord of lords,</hi> yet is <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God ſtiled <hi>A King of kings:</hi> And if ſo, then a Chriſtian King, as Gods Deputy, and having more then one Kingdome ſubject to him, may be termed <hi>a King of kings,</hi> and may ſubſtitute under him Viceroyes, Nobles and Judges, as helpers to bear the burden of governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under him, as well as Archbuilders, and Biſhops for ſacred matters.</p>
               <p>Yet the practice of the Pope of Rome is not at all war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted or countenanced hereby; but rather hence it may be argued that hee ſins moſt highly, 1. Becauſe, being an eccleſiaſticall man, he claimeth the ſecular and civill power alſo, and would have both ſwords: whereas <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoule is bidden to be ſubject to the higher power:</hi> and if every ſoule, then both <hi>Pauls</hi> and <hi>Peters,</hi> and much more the Popes. 2. The Popes ſins, that being an eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſon he claims ſuperiority over Kings and Princes in all the world; this extent of Soveraignty is Chriſts prerogative only. 3. That hee too little eſteemeth Gods Law, and too highly advanceth his owne Conſtitutions and Canons, and Doctrines, many of them needleſſe, or falſe, or contrary to Gods Lawes. But his pride is
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55646:20"/>abundantly manifeſt; therefore I ſay no more.</p>
               <p>Whereas his Orators plead in his behalf, that he is as far above the Emperor, or any King, in dignity, as the Sun before the Moon, Heaven before the Earth, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things before temporall; and, in regard that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning the ſoul are of more eſteem then matters of the body, he is above all Kings &amp; States in the world: I anſwer, In theſe things they groſly flatter him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves; for God, knowing the condition of humane nature to be frail, and the neceſſities incident to our bodies very many, appointed ſix dayes in ſpeciall for proviſion for the body, and but one in ſpeciall for his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the inſtruction of our ſouls; and yet the ſoul is of far greater dignity and worth then the body. And manifeſt it is that <hi>God ſet</hi> Moſes, David, <hi>and</hi> Solomon <hi>in place above</hi> Aaron, Abiathar, <hi>and</hi> Zadock; for though <hi>well</hi> and <hi>happy being</hi> is more excellent in it ſelf then <hi>meer being,</hi> yet ſeeing the <hi>care</hi> of <hi>being</hi> is in order &amp; progreſſe before <hi>well being,</hi> and in the way neceſſary thereunto, (for man muſt have a <hi>being,</hi> elſe he cannot have a <hi>well being</hi>) therefore God hath given the firſt and chief place to the King; that, 1. We may live, and enjoy <hi>a quiet and peaceable life,</hi> and not one become a prey to another. 2. <hi>Lead this life in all godlineſſe and honeſty</hi> by the Kings care, who provides for both theſe by ſubordinate civill, and eccleſiaſticall perſons. And for this cauſe it was and is, that though the duties of the Sabbath and ſervice of God are more excellent in themſelves then our food and care of our bodies; yet God will have mercy rather then ſacrifice, and diſpenſeth with ſacred duties, for the ſaving of mens lives, and neceſſary cure of diſeaſes.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:55646:20"/>
               <p>But on the other ſide, ſome object, The terme <hi>Biſhop</hi> is attributed to a <hi>Presbyter, Tit.</hi> 1.5, 7. and elſewhere: So that every Presbyter or Miniſter may bee truly called a Biſhop; and if ſo, then why ſhould there be an imparity maintained in this calling? I anſwer, The word <hi>Biſhop</hi> in its owne nature ſignifieth an Overſeer, or Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in any kinde, as <hi>Pakid</hi> in Hebrew. So God is <hi>The great Biſhop of all, Job</hi> 20.29. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. in vit Conſtant. l.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Conſtantine</hi> termes himſelfe <hi>Epiſcopon</hi> in one kind, his eccleſiaſticall chief Rulers in another. Heathen Authors ſtile <hi>God Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopon of all good and bad actions, and give the title alſo to civill Magiſtrates.</hi> In the like acception the 70. Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters uſe it, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 11.15. and elſewhere. It is alſo given to eccleſiaſticall Officers, as to <hi>Eleazar,</hi> who, though he was under <hi>Aaron,</hi> yet <hi>was Captain of the Captains over the Levites, Numb.</hi> 4.16. So 'tis <hi>to the Prieſts in office under</hi> Jehojadah, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 11.18. In the new Teſtament the 11. Apoſtles had the ſame <hi>Epiſcopen,</hi> Biſhoprick from which Judas <hi>fell, and into which</hi> Matthias <hi>was choſen, Act.</hi> 1.20. In the Church of Epheſus, <hi>thoſe which bee called Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters or Elders,</hi> that is, Miniſters (as by cuſtome now wee call them) are likewiſe called <hi>Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Overſeers</hi> over their flocks. Now, though the ſame terme be given to all theſe, yet the matter it ſelfe, and the very different de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of the perſons to whom it is given, admit not a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in any wiſe. The like is evident in other termes, Chriſt is <hi>Sar,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> Prince of peace; and <hi>Michael the great Sar,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 12.1.</note> Prince; <hi>The Kings of Perſia and Grecia</hi> are each of them called <hi>Sar;</hi> This very word is attributed to <hi>the</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of an army, To the</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">2 Chr. 18.25</note> 
                  <hi>Ruler of a City, To the chief</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">1 Chr. 27.22</note> 
                  <hi>Rulers of the Tribes, To the</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">1 Chr. 15.16, 27.</note> 
                  <hi>chief of the Levites, To the</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1 Chr. 24, 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Prince of the Sanctuary.</hi> Here then <hi>resipſa</hi> differenceth the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55646:21"/>term, and prevents miſpriſion &amp; confuſion. So like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the term <hi>Roſh,</hi> an Head or chiefe perſon, <hi>is ſpoken of</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">2 Ch. 13.12.</note> 
                  <hi>God, Of K.</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">1 Ch. 20.27.</note> Jehoſaphat, <hi>Of</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">2 Chr. 24.6.</note> Jehojadah <hi>the high Prieſt, Of other</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">1 Chr. 9.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſts, Of a</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Num. 7.11.</note> 
                  <hi>chief man of a Tribe, Of a</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Judg. 11.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Judge of Iſrael, Of the chiefe</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">1 Chr. 9.17.</note> 
                  <hi>doore keeper of the Temple, Of a</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">1 Chr. 11.6.</note> 
                  <hi>chiefe Captain.</hi> The like variety of acception is to bee found in the words <hi>Nagid,</hi> Prince, and <hi>Naſi,</hi> Ruler or Prelate. By all which it appeareth evidently, that the ſame terme may bee uſed of men much differing in place and degree, and having an imparity in their callings.</p>
               <p>So then, the term <hi>Biſhop</hi> being given to perſons of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall degrees, muſt be differenced according to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of their places. <hi>God is the Biſhop and great overſeer</hi> of all the world; <hi>Kings are now Overſeers</hi> of all kind of affairs in their kingdoms; <hi>Civill Magiſtrates are Biſhops</hi> in matters ſecular; <hi>Eleazar</hi> and <hi>Jehojadah</hi> were Biſhops over the Prieſts and Levites; <hi>The Apoſtles</hi> had each of them a Biſhoprick, &amp; ſuperintendency over the ſeverall nations to which they were ſent; <hi>The Elders of Epheſus were overſeers</hi> and Biſhops over their flocks; <hi>The Angels overſeers</hi> of the 7. Churches of Aſia, were their Biſhops; and S. <hi>John</hi> by Chriſt made a Biſhop over them. Thus, <hi>cum de rebus conſtet, vana eſt de verbis altercatio,</hi> ſeeing the things themſelves are plain, why ſhould wee ſtrive about words?</p>
               <p>But further it is objected, Seeing the term is common to many, why doth one only degree of men arrogate it to themſelves?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This ſcruple might well bee paſſed over; but men prone to take exception will not let ſlip any the leaſt atome. The caſe is cleare to any ſeriouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:55646:21"/>of one tongues borrowing words from another; for words ſo borrowed uſually by cuſtome vary from their primitive acception: And if cuſtome of ſpeech once bee taken up and become inveterate, neither the plaine origination of words, nor former practice of elder times once abandoned, nor the clear uſe of words in Scripture, nor any reaſon can prevaile againſt it. Our cares will not endure that a Maior of a Citie bee cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Biſhop of the ſame: for, though hee bee the Overſeer of it, the uſe of our Engliſh tongue will reject the calling of him Biſhop. Such a tyrant is Cuſtome, that <hi>Caeſar</hi> may make a free-man of a Citie, but cannot enfranchiſe a word. <hi>Loquendum ut vulgus</hi> is the old Rule; and therefore it would bee a vaine and idle quarrell to reaſon thus, Why ſhould <hi>Duke</hi> bee arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated to one degree of men, <hi>Herealt</hi> to another, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> to all people not Jewes or Chriſtians, <hi>Clergie</hi> to Church-men, <hi>Laity</hi> to the civill State, <hi>Martyr</hi> to ſuch onely as were put to death as witneſſes of Gods truth, <hi>Eccleſia</hi> to the Church of God; ſeeing <hi>Dux</hi> is any Leader, <hi>Herealt</hi> ſignifieth <hi>Herum altum,</hi> an high Lord, <hi>Ethnos</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Joh. 11.47.</note> ſignifies alſo the people of God, <hi>Cleros</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 4.20. &amp; 9.29. 1 Pet. 5.3.</note> all members of the Church, <hi>Laos</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 11.51.</note> the whole people <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 18.16.</note> one witneſſing to the truth, though never violently put to death for the ſame, <hi>Eccleſia</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 19.39.</note> a tumultuous aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Silver-ſmiths, &amp; the like? Cuſtome of the times reſtrained the ſignification of theſe words; and ſo of the word Biſhop. So that <hi>Biſhop</hi> in Greeke, whence it deſcends, is any Overſeer; but in our Engliſh, and ſome modern tongues, it is reſtrained and appropriated to one in place as Overſeer of the Clergy; a work of ſingular uſe, if well performed.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:55646:22"/>
               <p>Secondly, Nor doth the cuſtome of our ſpeech only in the practice of theſe our times make for this, but Scripture it ſelfe ſhews the prevalency of cuſtome, and how uſe takes up and warrants ſome words for currant, and lyes by others. So hee of ancient time was
<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 9.9.</note> called <hi>Rhoe,</hi> a Seer, whom afterwards cuſtome nominated <hi>Nabi,</hi> a Prophet; And whereas neither doth God give, nor <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> take to themſelves in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Scripture the title of <hi>Sarim,</hi> Princes; but <hi>Korah</hi> and his adherents lay that to their charge, that they made
<note n="g" place="margin">Num. 16.13</note> themſelves <hi>Sarim,</hi> Princes and Rulers, ſo that there the word is firſt uſed, and in <hi>Korah</hi>'s malice at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prieſts: God, who made them Rulers over the Prieſts, though hee never before (ſo farre as I know) gave them that title, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward doth frequently ſtile the Prieſts <hi>Sarim,</hi> Princes, or chiefe Rulers in ſacred performances, to ſee them duly obſerved. Wee know alſo, that the name <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle</hi> was given to the twelve, and afterward to <hi>Paul, Matthias,</hi> and others: but yet in the Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of Aſia, <hi>Angel,</hi> a terme equivalent, is uſed. Afterward, as by the writings of ſucceeding times is evident, the chiefe Eccleſiaſticall perſon in any Church was not called <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> but <hi>Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, Biſhop,</hi> or <hi>Papas</hi> Father, or <hi>Patriarch</hi> chiefe Father, and the word Apoſtle given commonly to the twelve, and to <hi>Paul,</hi> ſo often called Apoſtle that no cuſtome could take it from him; and the terme <hi>Angel</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to the miniſtring Spirits, Gods meſſengers. Alſo the terme Presbyter denoted any ancient eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall man in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, as <hi>even the Apoſtles themſelves,</hi> 2 <hi>John</hi> 1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1. inſomuch that the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55646:22"/>name of <hi>Presbyter is attributed to the twenty foure ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on Thrones, and having Crownes on their heads, Revel.</hi> 4.4. Theſe wee may conceive to bee Angels of the Churches, and ſo called, when ſpeech was of them, with reference to the Churches to which they had their miſſion; but in preſence of the Lambe they riſe from their Thrones, and caſt downe their Crowns, and are termed Presbyters: ſo a deputed Officer, in preſence of his Prince, ſtands by as a private man, and layes downe the enſignes of his honour. Yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times appropriated the title Presbyter, that is, Prieſt, to them whom wee call Miniſters; and ſince that, cuſtome hath ſo prevailed, that the terme <hi>Prieſt</hi> is by our common people and others confined to a Popiſh Prieſt, nor will they well endure to have the word righted according to his ancient acception, and have <hi>Presbyter</hi> tranſlated <hi>Prieſt;</hi> which might juſtly be done, if cuſtome would give leave.</p>
               <p>And thirdly, As the Apoſtles imparted the titles of <hi>Apoſtle, Presbyter, Deacon, Watchmen, Souldiers, Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen, Labourers, Teachers, Paſtours,</hi> to others; ſo likewiſe they left the title of <hi>Biſhop</hi> (for each of them had <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a Biſhoprick, as above) to Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call men ſucceeding them. Only after times appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated ſome of theſe Titles to certaine degrees of men, as the prevalency of cuſtome ſettled them, and diſtinction of termes was entertained to avoyd confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and miſpriſion, when the Church of God was much enlarged. The Church is now, and ever was a Body conſiſting of ſeverall members; ſome <hi>in this</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Body are eyes, ſome hands, ſome feet,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſome</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Luk. 22.26.</note> 
                  <hi>are greater and chiefe, ſome leſſe in the Kingdome of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:55646:23"/>The leſſe have a leſſe ſervice or charge, the greater and chiefe are or ſhould bee of greater ſervice and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for the good of the whole; and ſo they are indeed, though it may ſeeme otherwiſe. A prudent and conſiderate man will not judge the belly in the Roman Apologue to bee idler then the other parts; nor the Maſter of the Ship, ſitting at the Sterne, a leſſe actor for the welfare of the paſſengers, then they which tug at the oares, or hoyſe or ſtrike ſaile: As the hand and foot are content with their owne offices, ſo ſhould each member in the Church: but yet there is a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in ſome regard; for one of inferiour place in the Church may deſire the improvement of his talent and abilities, may deſire <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as was ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove. As Saint <hi>Paul</hi> approves this, ſo the practice of the primitive times ſhew it then to have beene uſuall; <hi>Matthias</hi> of a Diſciple was made an Apoſtle, <hi>Philip</hi> of a Deacon became an Evangeliſt.</p>
               <p>Furthermore, concerning the performance of theſe Eccleſiaſticall offices, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaking of, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly reckoning up <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods gifts, ſheweth a more excellent way</hi> to uſe them; namely, That whatſoever gift of God in this kinde any one hath, hee ſhould above all make uſe of <hi>Chriſtian love: without which, tongues, propheſie, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, faith, and all other gifts and graces are nothing:</hi> and with which Chriſtian love, if any ones heart bee truly enflamed, hee will apply himſelfe to doe good in the Church in whatſoever kinde hee can, as Paſtor, as Deacon, as a fellow-workman, as a Presbyter, as an helper, &amp;c. yea, doe any uſefull ſervice in the Church, as God gives ability, and occaſion is offered. So Saint
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55646:23"/>
                  <hi>John,</hi> being an Apoſtle, did as a Prophet write the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, and as an Evangeliſt alſo his Goſpel, a divine ſupplement to the three other Goſpels, and then his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles. <hi>Paul</hi> ſent forth to preach, did ſometimes bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, performed the part of a Deacon, and Evangeliſt; yea, became all things to all men.</p>
               <p>But how may it appeare that any one, as a Biſhop, had many Presbyters and Deacons under him? or had a Dioceſſe, or a large circuit of a country to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeen by him? <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Wee may obſerve that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, in regard of thepaucity of labourers in the great harveſt of God, had large (as I may call them) Dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and that each of them ſettled Presbyters in many Cities, as we conceive by that which we read of ſome of them. It is alſo manifeſt, that there were many Presbyters at once <hi>in</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Epheſus, Acts</hi> 20. <hi>in Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 11.30. in <hi>Antioch, Act.</hi> 13.1.
<note n="b" place="margin">Act. 11.30.</note> at <hi>Caeſarea</hi> there were at one time <hi>Philip</hi> the Evangeliſt, <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Act. 13.1.</note> and the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of his travels, <hi>Agabus</hi> and <hi>Luke.</hi> Theſe would not have ſtayed there, but that there was worke for more then one of them: Seeing profeſſours of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity much increaſed, and the Apoſtles endevoured to hold them in the true faith, and ſtill to convert more Proſelites, it neceſſarily followeth, that they would not ſee them want any needfull ſupply of Teachers and Inſtructors; but ſent their Miniſters and helpers to any Church, as any preſent occaſion required; and that they call'd them back, as they found neceſſary and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for any other place. And ſeeing ſome Cities were large and had many
<note n="a" place="margin">Act. 13.5.</note> Synagogues (which the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles made uſe of, and ſo probably ſuch as were by them ſent, or left there to preach) it was requiſite that
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55646:24"/>they ſhould have more then one Presbyter for the ſame, over which <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Angell of the Church was left. When the reſt of the twelve Apoſtles were dead, and Saint <hi>John</hi> onely left alive, but aged he not able to viſit ſome remote Churches in his own perſon, by writing to the ſeven Churches of Aſia, informed <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one, who had an eare in any Church whatſoever, to heare</hi> their duties. Theſe Angels might, according to the example of <hi>Titus</hi> left by <hi>Paul</hi> in Creet, ordaine Presbyters in every of their Cities: They might alſo <hi>try thoſe, who ſaid</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Rev. 3.9. Rev. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>they were Jewes,</hi> that is, Chriſtians, and might <hi>examine them, who pretended to be Apoſtles,</hi> and were found lyars. Had not theſe ſeven Churches more then one Teacher entertained in them, no ſtranger would have <hi>fained</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Say he was an Apoſtle.</note> 
                  <hi>a miſsion</hi> unto any of them: and if the Angell of a Church exerciſed his power to examine and reject falſe pretenders, we ſee thereby what his authority was; for he who could do thus by a ſtranger, might doe as much by a Presbyter bred up in his owne Church.</p>
               <p>As for Dioceſſes, the thing is ancient: For the great Cities of old had ſome Pagi or villages neer adjoyned and ſubordinate to them. Hence we read of
<note n="a" place="margin">Joſ. 15.</note> Gilead, Ekron, &amp;c. and their villages: of Jeruſalem
<note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 16.</note> and her daughters. Of this there is no need to doubt, becauſe it is uſuall in all Countries whatſoever, as being a thing for many reaſons expedient; and therefore wee may well grant that Epheſus, Smyrna, Philadelphia, &amp;c. had ſome villages depending on them, and ſubject to them, and that therein ſome free men of the chiefe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties did <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, inhabit. And thus the thing is ancient, how late ſoever ſome affirme the name to be. Men al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55646:24"/>have uſed of old <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to dwell together for mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall defence and comfort one of another: ſo that the thing here alſo is ancient, and was fitted of old for the name of Chriſtian Pariſhes.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe there were ſuch adjacent villages to the great Cities, and that the retired perſons, and ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards there harkned as ſoon or ſooner to the Goſpel then the richer and greater Citizens, who were cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred with worldly imployments, &amp; burdened with the weight of honourable places; becauſe alſo the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards of Bethlehem, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> of Arimathea, and the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, coaſts neer adjoyning to the more noble Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were often more attentive to the Goſpel, then the great men in Jeruſalem and other large Cities: ſuppoſe all this, yet how will it appeare, that theſe Angels or chief Overſeers of the Churches, had ſuch large re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues as ſome Biſhops in theſe our dayes? <hi>Anſwer.</hi> To this an anſwer is eaſily made: No man can expect that a river ſhould have ſo great a ſtream at or neer the ſpring head, as it hath after many miles running; 'Tis not poſſible that a Lords, or Knights houſe in New-England ſhould be as well built, furniſhed and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a Lords or Knights houſe uſually in Old-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. The Angels and Presbyters of the primitive times found ſtronger oppoſition from the potent Romans and cruell Heathen, and had much more to doe to keep off the violent hands of malicious perſecutors, then the New-Englanders to withſtand the unarmed Salvages, and to build and ſettle themſelves in their neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood. If now in the Lands, which have long entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Chriſtianity, the goodneſſe of God, and the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſtian Princes, and worthy private men under
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55646:25"/>them have, as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> and their Nobles, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided for the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate, and endowed them with a propriety in a larger Revenue then the Apoſtles times enjoyed, we have greater cauſe to bleſſe God for all, and to ſound forth his praiſe in ſacred hymnes, as <hi>David</hi> cauſed to be done: That other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſeeing the righteous flouriſh, and abundance of peace, made uſe of in due manner for Gods glory, may rejoyce and ſay, <hi>Happy are the people which are in ſuch a ſtate, yea bleſſed are they, which have the Lord for their God;</hi> who upon a right ſeeking of his kingdome, addes over and above temporall benefits, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.33. The Civill and Eccleſiaſticall ſtate have in all times endured affliction or proſperity alike and joyntly. God extraordinarily provided for his People and Prieſts Manna and quailes in the barren wilderneſſe; but in Canaan gave the People corne, wine and oyle in plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Prieſts tithes, his own portion, free will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and conſecrate things of great worth, given by <hi>David, Solomon,</hi> their worthies, and other devout per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſo God firſt provided for his Apoſtles, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp;c. extraordinarily by the ſelling of the beleevers poſſeſſions; but afterward by free gifts of bountifull perſons conferred on them, according to the plenty and peace of their times, they were furniſhed with more plentifull meanes to live cheerfully, and to undergoe their weighty charge with comfort and alacrity; and, as God gave more and more increaſe unto them, to build, and endow Colledges, Schools, and Hoſpitals. If <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> and <hi>Job,</hi> and other religious ſacrificers were not the ſlacker, but more frequent in their ſacred duties, and inſtruction of their people; why ſhould plenty of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55646:25"/>meanes and outward eſtate be thought to dull and take off the edge of Eccleſiaſticall perſons from their ſacred offices and performances? The ſame might, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did befall of old; ſo prone is man to ſin: but Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall perſons have (and ſhould make uſe of) their religious knowledge to uſe temporall things aright; if they doe not, good Lawes eſtabliſhed in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Common-wealth are of force to prevent or cure that malady. The Goſpel by Gods great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as it hath brought unto us a better covenant, and better promiſes; ſo it hath bettered and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged the temporall meanes of all eſtates: Is it fit here to make the Eccleſiaſticall eſtate an exception from the generall? Let that, I pray you, be duly conſidered: God, thankes be unto him for his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious goodneſſe, hath now made roome enough for his people, as for Iſrael in Canaan: and what needs ſhips having ſea roome at will to claſh and fall foule one againſt another? God is good unto all, and can open the windowes of heaven and poure out a bleſſing on all eſtates. Onely let the civill and ſpirituall eſtates, as two ſtrong pillars, mutually conjoyne their forces, and in Chriſtian love ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port the whole frame of the building, and ſo make each other the more ſteady and ſtrong.</p>
               <p>But further, Is it fit that our eccleſiaſticall perſons ſhould bee termed Lords?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſwer,</hi> firſt, It pleaſed God (as above was ſhewed) to vouchſafe titles of his owne to Civill and Eccleſiaſticall perſons; as theſe to the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall, <hi>Sar</hi> Prince, <hi>Naſi</hi> Prelate, <hi>Roſh</hi> head, <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitecton</hi> chiefe builder, &amp;c. Theſe, as alſo the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55646:26"/>terme <hi>Adon,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Lord,</hi> are in the higheſt and moſt eminent ſenſe due to God onely, for hee is a Lord doing what ever hee pleaſeth of his owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: yet in an inferiour and ſubordinate ſenſe, <hi>Sara</hi> called <hi>Abraham Lord;</hi> ſo did the Hittite, <hi>Geneſis</hi> 23. <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſervant is called <hi>Lord, Geneſis</hi> 24.18. So is any maſter of ſervants, <hi>Exodus</hi> 21.5. <hi>Col.</hi> 4.7. and (which comes home to this preſent objection) one of the foure and twenty Presbyters. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 7.14. is called <hi>Lord:</hi> And if ſo, then this terme is not denyable to Biſhops.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as others in chiefe places ſubordinate to Princes are high and honourable Lords, ſo may the chiefe Eccleſiaſticall perſons be venerable and reverend Lords: becauſe in all times, from the worlds beginning untill Chriſts dayes, Eccleſiaſticall perſons were of great eſteeme: in the primitive times they were chiefe governours of the Church under Chriſt; and for their ſacred imployments ſake, being men anſwerable to their calling, ought doubtleſſe to have a neer ſubordination to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Princes; and if the kingdome of God by their vigilancy be firſt and chiefly ſought, all other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of this world wilbe the more proſperous.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Though God in ſome ſenſe (as above) doth deny certain titles to men, yet he never was againſt words of due reſpect and obſervance to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours; nor indeed are ſuch words blame worthy: ſo that they be not
<note n="a" place="margin">As <hi>Judas</hi> his <hi>Haile Maſter.</hi>
                  </note> bare and meer complement, and not cordiat: or
<note n="b" place="margin">As was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> applauſe. Acts 12.19.</note> hyperbolicall to puffe up men with pride. Yea, I know not whether due titles bee not now more ſtudiouſly and frequently fitted to
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55646:26"/>mens perſons: Becauſe, 1. Some ſects ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to vilifie them. 2. Becauſe 'tis not amiſſe thereby to put ſome great ones in minde to be Lords, defending the innocent, as well as to have a title to rule over others in the Lord: to be Lords providing for the welfare of all under them, as well as to have a power comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them. God hath been bountifull to Eccleſiaſticall perſons many wayes, and they who truely conſider that, will not be ſtrict handed to them.</p>
               <p>What hath been here ſpoken in their behalfe, was occaſioned by ſome, who upon faulty arguments (as I conceive) judge amiſſe of their places and callings: Theſe have (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in like caſe ſaid) compelled mee to ſpeak what I by Gods word finde to bee truth in this point, and ſubmit whatſoever I have herein written to the religious, grave, and mature judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all who bee growne men in Chriſt, and by reaſon of uſe have their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and evill.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
